<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-grow-large-communities-usage-02" ipr="trust200902">
    <front>
        <title>Usage of BGP Large Communities</title>

        <author fullname="Job Snijders" initials="J." surname="Snijders">
            <organization abbrev="NTT">NTT Communications</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Theodorus Majofskistraat 100</street>
                    <code>1065 SZ</code>
                    <city>Amsterdam</city>
                    <country>The Netherlands</country>
                </postal>
                <email>job@ntt.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="John Heasley" initials="J." surname="Heasley">
            <organization abbrev="NTT">NTT Communications</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>12160 NW Coleman Drive</street>
                    <city>Portland</city>
                    <region>OR</region>
                    <code>97229</code>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </postal>
                <email>heas@shrubbery.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>


        <author fullname="Martijn Schmidt" initials="M." surname="Schmidt">
            <organization>i3D.net</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Rivium 1e Straat 1</street>
                    <code>2909 LE</code>
                    <city>Capelle aan den IJssel</city>
                    <country>NL</country>
                </postal>
                <email>martijnschmidt@i3d.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date/>

        <area>Routing</area>
        <workgroup>Global Routing Operations</workgroup>
        <keyword>large</keyword>
        <keyword>BGP</keyword>
        <keyword>communities</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
                Examples and inspiration for operators for the use of BGP Large
                Communities.
            </t>
        </abstract>

        <note title="Requirements Language">
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
                this document are to be interpreted as described in
                <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
            </t>
        </note>

    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
                <xref target="RFC8092">BGP Large Communities</xref> provide a mechanism to signal opaque information between Autonomous Systems.
                This document presents a set of examples of how Large BGP Communities could be utilised by an operator to achieve various goals.
                This document draws from experience in Operational Communities such as <eref target="http://nanog.net">NANOG</eref> and <eref target="http://nlnog.net">NLNOG</eref>.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="The Generic Design Pattern">
            <t>
                Large BGP Communities are composed of three 4-octet fields.
                The first is the Global Administrator field, whose value is the Autonomous System (ASN) that has defined the meaning of the remaining two 4-octet fields, the Local Data fields.
                This document describes an approach defining these fields as "ASN:Function:Parameter".
            </t>
            <t>
                In contemporary deployments of both BGP Communities <xref target="RFC1997"/> and BGP Large Communities, functionality can be divided into two categories:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>Informational Communities</t>
                    <t>Action Communities</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>
                Throughout the document a topology of four Autonomous Systems is used to illustrate the usage of Communities in the following configuration:
<figure align="center"><artwork><![CDATA[
        AS 65551
            |
            ^
            |
        AS 64497
          /  \
         ^    \
        /      ^
   AS 64498     \
       |        | 
       `<->- AS 64499
]]></artwork></figure>
                AS 64497 obtains transit services from AS 65551, a 32-bit ASN.
                AS 64497 provides transit services to both AS 64498 and AS 64499.
                AS 64498 and AS 64499 maintain a peering relationship in which they only exchange their customer routes.
            </t>
            <t>
                The opaque nature of BGP Large Communities allows for rapid deployment of new features or changes to products.
                Operators are encouraged to publicly publish and maintain documentation of the purpose of each Large BGP Community, both informational and action, that they support or are visible in looking glasses.
            </t>
            <section title="Informational Communities">
                <t>
                    Informational Communites are labels for attributes such as the origin of the route announcement, the nature of the relation with the EBGP neighbor or the intended propagation audience.
                    Informational Communities can also assist in providing valuable information for day-to-day network operations such as debugging or capacity planning.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The Global Administrator field is set to the ASN which marks the routes with the Informational Communities.
                    For example, AS 64497 might add a community with the GA 64497 to a route accepted from an IBGP or EBGP neighbor as a means of signalling that it was imported in a certain geographical region.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In general, the intended audiences of Informational Communities are downstream networks and the Global Administrator itself, but any Autonomous System could benefit from receiving these communities.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Action Communities">
                <t>
                    Action Communities are added as a label to request non-default treatment of a route by having the operator's defined routing policy adjust variables such as its propagation characteristics, the LOCAL_PREFENCE, the next-hop, or the number of AS_PATH prepends to be added when exporting or importing a route to/from another AS.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The Global Administrator field is set to the ASN which has defined the functionality of that Large Community and is therefore expected to perform the action.
                    For instance, AS 64499 might label a route with a Large Community containing GA 64497 to signal AS 64497 a request to perform a pre-defined action upon that route.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In general, the intended audiences of Action Communities are upstream providers and the Global Administrator itself, but in theory any AS could act as the audience if they are willing to do so.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Examples of Informational Communities">
            <section title="Location">
                <t>
                    AS 64497 may inform other networks about the geographical region where AS 64497 imported a route by marking it with BGP Large Communities following one of the following schemes or a combination thereof.
                </t>
                <section title="An ISO 3166-1 numeric function">
                    <t>
                        AS 64497 could assign a value of 1 to the first Local Data field to designate the content of the second Local Data field as an ISO-3166-1 numeric country identifier. 
                    </t>
                    <texttable title="Information: ISO 3166-1" anchor='info_iso3166'>
                        <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                        <c>64497:1:528</c><c>Route learned in the Netherlands</c>
                        <c>64497:1:392</c><c>Route learned in Japan</c>
                        <c>64497:1:840</c><c>Route learned in the United States of America</c>
                        <postamble>
                            Example documentation for Informational Communities deployed by AS 64497 to describe the location where a route was imported using ISO 3166-1 numeric identifiers.
                        </postamble>
                    </texttable>
                </section>
                <section title="A UNSD Region function">
                    <t>
                        AS 64497 could assign a value of 2 to the first Local Data field to designate the content of the second Local Data field as a number published by the <eref target="http://unstats.un.org/unsd/methods/m49/m49regin.htm">United Nations Statistics Division</eref> for macro geographical (continental) regions, geographical sub-regions, or selected economic and other groupings.
                    </t>
                    <texttable title="Information: UNSD Regions" anchor='info_regions'>
                        <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                        <c>64497:2:2</c><c>Route learned in Africa</c>
                        <c>64497:2:9</c><c>Route learned in Oceania</c>
                        <c>64497:2:145</c><c>Route learned in Western Asia</c>
                        <c>64497:2:150</c><c>Route learned in Europe</c>
                        <postamble>
                            Example documentation for Informational Communities deployed by AS 64497 to describe the location where a route was imported using numeric identifiers published by the United Nations Statistics Division.
                        </postamble>
                    </texttable>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Relation">
                <t>
                    AS 64497 could assign a value of 3 to the first Local Data field to designate the content of the second Local Data field as a number indicating whether the route was originated inside its own network, or if it was instead learned externally and how its relation with that specific EBGP neighbor can be characterized.
                </t>
                <texttable title="Information: Relation" anchor='info_relation'>
                    <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                    <c>64497:3:1</c><c>Route originated internally</c>
                    <c>64497:3:2</c><c>Route learned from a customer</c>
                    <c>64497:3:3</c><c>Route learned from a peering partner</c>
                    <c>64497:3:4</c><c>Route learned from an upstream provider</c>
                    <postamble>
                        Example documentation for Informational Communities
                        deployed by AS 64497 to describe the relation to the
                        ASN from which the route was received.
                    </postamble>
                </texttable>
            </section>
            <section title="Combining Informational Communities">
                <t>
                    Multiple Informational Communities may be tagged on a route, for example: a route learned in the Netherlands from a customer could contain communities 64497:1:528, 64497:2:150 and 64497:3:2 at the same time.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Examples of Action Communities">
            <section title="Selective NO_EXPORT">
                <t>
                    As part of a commercial agreement between AS 64497 and AS 64498, AS 64497 might expose BGP traffic engineering features to AS 64498.
                    One such BGP traffic engineering feature could be selectively not exporting routes learned from AS 64498 to certain EBGP neighbors of AS 64497.
                </t>
                <section title="Peer ASN Based Selective NO_EXPORT">
                    <t>
                        AS 64497 could assign a value of 4 to the first Local Data field to designate the content of the second Local Data field as a neighboring ASN to which the prevention of direct route propagation is requested.
                    </t>
                    <texttable title="Action: Peer ASN NO_EXPORT" anchor='action_peer_no_export'>
                        <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                        <c>64497:4:2914</c><c>Do not export route to AS 2914</c>
                        <c>64497:4:7018</c><c>Do not export route to AS 7018</c>
                        <c>64497:4:65551</c><c>Do not export route to AS 65551</c>
                        <postamble>
                            Example documentation for Action Communities deployed by AS 64497 to expose a BGP traffic engineering feature which selectively prevents the direct propagation of routes to the neighboring ASN listed in the second Local Data field.
                        </postamble>
                    </texttable>
                </section>
                <section title="Location Based Selective NO_EXPORT">
                    <t>
                        AS 64497 could assign a value of 5 to the first Local Data field to designate the content of the second Local Data field as an ISO 3166-1 numeric country identifier in which the prevention of direct route propagation to certain EBGP neighbors is requested.
                        This might however not prevent one of those EBGP neighbors from learning that route in another region and in turn making it available in the targeted country.
                    </t>
                    <texttable title="Action: NO_EXPORT in Region" anchor='action_region_no_export'>
                        <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                        <c>64497:5:528</c><c>Do not export to EBGP neighbors in the Netherlands</c>
                        <c>64497:5:392</c><c>Do not export to EBGP neighbors in Japan</c>
                        <c>64497:5:840</c><c>Do not export to EBGP neighbors in the United States of America</c>
                        <postamble>
                            Example documentation for Action Communities deployed by AS 64497 to expose a BGP traffic engineering feature which selectively prevents the direct propagation of routes to all EBGP neighbors in the geographical region listed in the second Local Data field.
                        </postamble>
                    </texttable>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section title="Selective AS_PATH Prepending">
                <t>
                    As part of a commercial agreement between AS 64497 and AS 64498, AS 64497 might expose BGP traffic engineering features to AS 64498.
                    One such BGP traffic engineering feature could be selectively prepending the AS_PATH with AS 64497 to certain certain EBGP neighbors of AS 64497.
                </t>
                <section title="Peer ASN Based Selective AS_PATH Prepending">
                    <t>
                        AS 64497 could assign a value of 6 to the first Local Data field to designate the content of the second Local Data field as a neighboring ASN to which prepending of the AS_PATH with AS 64497 is requested upon direct propagation of the route.
                    </t>
                    <texttable title="Action: Prepend to Peer ASN " anchor='action_peer_prepend'>
                        <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                        <c>64497:6:2914</c><c>Prepend 64497 once on export to AS 2914</c>
                        <c>64497:6:7018</c><c>Prepend 64497 once on export to AS 7018</c>
                        <c>64497:6:65551</c><c>Prepend 64497 once on export to AS 65551</c>
                        <postamble>
                            Example documentation for Action Communities deployed by AS 64497 to expose a BGP traffic engineering feature which selectively prepends the AS_PATH with AS 64497 when propagating the route to a certain EBGP neighbor. 
                        </postamble>
                    </texttable>
                </section>
                <section title="Location Based Selective AS_PATH Prepending">
                    <t>
                        AS 64497 could assign a value of 7 to the first Local Data field to designate the content of the second Local Data field as an ISO 3166-1 numeric country identifier to which the prepending of the AS_PATH with AS 64497 is requested upon direct propagation of the route to all EBGP neighbors in that region.
                    </t>
                    <texttable title="Action: Prepend in Region" anchor='action_region_prepend'>
                        <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                        <c>64497:7:528</c><c>Prepend once to EBGP neighbors in the Netherlands</c>
                        <c>64497:7:392</c><c>Prepend once to EBGP neighbors in Japan</c>
                        <c>64497:7:840</c><c>Prepend once to EBGP neighbors in United States of America</c>
                        <postamble>
                            Example documentation for Action Communities deployed by AS 64497 to expose a BGP traffic engineering feature which selectively prepends the AS_PATH with AS 64497 when propagating the route to all EBGP neighbors in the geographical region listed in the second Local Data field.
                        </postamble>
                    </texttable>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section title="Manipulation of the LOCAL_PREF attribute">
                <t>
                    As part of a commercial agreement between AS 64497 and AS 64498, AS 64497 might expose BGP traffic engineering features to AS 64498.
                    One such BGP traffic engineering feature might allow AS 64498 to manipulate the value of the LOCAL_PREF attribute which AS 64497 assigns to routes learned from AS 64498, even though the LOCAL_PREF attribute is not sent to EBGP neighbors in BGP UPDATE messages.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Since the LOCAL_PREF attribute values assigned to routes are locally significant within each Autonomous System, it is not practical to list them in this document.
                    Instead, it could be useful to classify the major types of route likely to exist within an Autonomous System's routing hierarchy and expose an ability to set one's route to the corresponding LOCAL_PREF value.
                    The following non-exhaustive list places the major types of route in order of descending LOCAL_PREF value and assigns a function identifier which could be used in the first Local Data field of a BGP Large Community:
                </t>
                <texttable title="Action: Preference Function Identifiers" anchor='action_pref_func'>
                    <ttcol align='center'>Function</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='left'>Preference Class</ttcol>
                    <c>8</c><c>Normal customer route.</c>
                    <c>9</c><c>Backup customer route.</c>
                    <c>10</c><c>Peering route.</c>
                    <c>11</c><c>Upstream transit route.</c>
                    <c>12</c><c>Fallback route, to be installed if no other path is available.</c>
                </texttable>
                <section title="Global Manipulation of LOCAL_PREF">
                    <t>
                        AS 64497 could place one of the pre-defined function identifiers in the first Local Data field and set the value 0 in the second Local Data field to designate that the LOCAL_PREF associated with that function identifier should be applied for that route throughout the whole Autonomous System.
                    </t>
                    <texttable title="Action: Global LOCAL_PREF Manipulation" anchor='action_pref_global'>
                        <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                        <c>64497:9:0</c><c>Assign LOCAL_PREF for a customer backup route</c>
                        <c>64497:10:0</c><c>Assign LOCAL_PREF for a peering route</c>
                        <c>64497:12:0</c><c>Assign LOCAL_PREF for a fallback route</c>
                        <postamble>
                            Example documentation for Action Communities deployed by AS 64497 to expose a BGP traffic engineering feature which allows a BGP neighbor to manipulate the LOCAL_PREF attribute for the route within AS 64497's Autonomous System on a global basis.
                        </postamble>
                    </texttable>
                </section>
                <section title="Location Based Manipulation of LOCAL_PREF">
                    <t>
                        AS 64497 could place one of the pre-defined function identifiers in the first Local Data field and use an ISO 3166-1 numeric country identifier in the second Local Data field to designate the geographical region in which the non-default LOCAL_PREF associated with that function identifier should be applied to the route.
                        The value of the LOCAL_PREF attribute should not deviate from the default for that route type in all regions not targeted by one or more of these Action Communities.
                    </t>
                    <texttable title="Action: Regional LOCAL_PREF Manipulation" anchor='action_pref_region'>
                        <ttcol align='center'>BGP Large Community</ttcol>
                        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                        <c>64497:9:528</c><c>Assign LOCAL_PREF for a customer backup route on IBGP speakers in the Netherlands</c>
                        <c>64497:10:392</c><c>Assign LOCAL_PREF for a peering route on IBGP speakers in Japan</c>
                        <c>64497:12:840</c><c>Assign LOCAL_PREF for a fallback route on IBGP speakers in United States of America</c>
                        <postamble>
                            Example documentation for Action Communities deployed by AS 64497 to expose a BGP traffic engineering feature which allows a BGP neighbor to selectively manipulate the LOCAL_PREF attribute on IBGP speakers in the geographical region listed in the second Local Data field.
                        </postamble>
                    </texttable>
                </section>
                <t>
                    The degree of preference learned via the LOCAL_PREF attribute strongly influences the BGP Decision Process, which in turn affects the scope of route propagation to other BGP neighbors.
                    Therefore, Operators should take special care when using Action Communities that decrease the degree of preference stored in the LOCAL_PREF attribute to a value below that of another major route type.
                    Some of the unintended BGP states that might arise as a result of these traffic engineering decisions are described as "BGP Wedgies" in <xref target="RFC4264"/>.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                Network operators should note the recommendations in Section 11 of BGP Operations and Security <xref target="RFC7454"/>.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
                None.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>
                The authors would like to gratefully acknowledge the insightful comments, contributions, critique and support from Adam Chappell, Jonathan Stewart, and Will Hargrave.
            </t>
        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1997"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7454"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4264"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8092"?>
        </references>
<!--
            <references title="Informative References">
            </references>
-->


        </back>
    </rfc>
